<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"> 
<chapter id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <section>
        <title>Overview</title>
        <para>
            Spring-WS consists of three separate modules. This chapter discusses each of the modules in turn.
        </para>
        <para>
            The <link linkend="ws">Core</link> package is the central part of the Web services functionality. It
            provides the central <classname>WebServiceMessage</classname> and <classname>SoapMessage</classname>
            interfaces, the powerful message dispatching, and the various support classes for implementing Web service
            endpoints.
        </para>
        <para>
            The <link linkend="security">Security</link> package provides a WS-Security implementation that integrates
            with the core Web service package. It allows you to add principal tokens, sign, and decrypt and encrypt SOAP
            messages. Addtionally, it allows you to leverage your existing Acegi security implementation for
            authentication and authorization.
        </para>
        <para>
            The <link linkend="oxm">OXM</link> package provides integration for popular XML marshalling APIs, including
            JAXB 1 and 2. Using the OXM package means that you benefit from a unified exception hierarchy, and can wire
            up your favorite XML marshalling technology easily.
        </para>
    </section>


    <section>
        <title>Why Spring Web Services?</title>
        <para>
            There are various other SOAP stacks available, why and where should you use Spring-WS? This section answers
            that question by showing what the focus of Spring-WS is.
        </para>
        <section>
            <title>Spring-WS is meant for Public Web Services</title>
            <para>
                One can distinguish between two different sorts of Web services. Private Web services are not used
                outside your application domain. They might form a part of your Enterprise Service Bus, or used as a
                means to communicate between a fat .NET client and a J2EE server. When the two sides of the spectrum
                (client and server) are under your control, you can easily expose (existing) methods, since you can
                (re)generate client code easily.
            </para>
            <para>
                Public Web services provide a separate interface to your application. They are often used by clients
                that are outside of your reach. When developing a public Web service, you should really think about the
                interface you are providing: it is probably going to be around for a while, and you cannot change it
                that often. As such, it is a good idea to place the Web service in a separate layer, thus hiding the
                inner workings of the application. As a result, you can change the Web service and the rest of the
                appliciation seperately.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Spring-WS makes Web Services First Class Citizens of the Architecture</title>
            <para>
                Web Services deserve a proper place in an application architecture. Often, they exist as an afterthought
                in the application architecture, mostly because existing Java business interfaces are exposed as SOAP
                services. One could say that they are "SOAPified". Spring-WS provides a MVC-like framework for
                developing a Web service application layer, just like you would develop a layer especially for a Web
                user interface using Spring-MVC. Spring-WS also provides useful integration points with you existing
                Spring application architecture, such as the Acegi integration.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Spring-WS is Data-Driven</title>
            <para>
                When Web Services started making their way into the Enterprise Computing world, developers considered
                Web Services just another, XML-based remoting protocol. Such remoting frameworks can be used with
                relative ease: on the server-side, one simply implements a specific interface such as
                <classname>java.rmi.Remote</classname>, and on the client side, a dynamic proxy is used.
                Unfortunately, because of this simplicity, remoting architectures have some issues:
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            They pretend there is no <emphasis>latency</emphasis> between the client and the server,
                            while in fact there is both network and application latency,
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            They pretend that client and server have <emphasis>shared memory access</emphasis>, while in
                            fact data must be both marshalled and unmarshalled,
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            They ignore the possibility of a <emphasis>request or response not reaching its
                            destination</emphasis>,
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            They enforce a <emphasis>non-concurrent</emphasis> programming model, while in fact a
                            concurrent approach seems more in place,
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            They enforce a <emphasis>tightly coupled architecture</emphasis>, where changes on the
                            server-side result in changes on the client-side.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                It is not without reason that Gregor Hohpe calls a distributed architecture a <quote>fairy tale
                architecture</quote>: one is made to believe things that simply are not true. To quote <xref
                linkend="waldo-94"/>:
                <blockquote>
                    <para>
                        Objects that interact in a distributed system need to be dealt with in ways that are
                        intrinsically different from objects that interact in a single address space.
                    </para>
                </blockquote>
            </para>
            <para>
                Instead of being behavior-driven, Spring-WS is data-driven: it focusses on the data being sent, not on a
                particular method being invoked.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Spring-WS Focusses on Contract-first Development</title>
            <para>
                SOAP services are defined in two contracts: the data contract (the XSD schema), and the service contract
                (the WSDL). Generating these contracts from Java-code is called <emphasis>contract-last
                development</emphasis> <xref linkend="alpine"/> identifies some problems with this approach, most
                importantly:
                <blockquote>
                    <para>
                        There is no way to ensure that a service’s published interface remains constant over time.
                        Every redeployment of the service may change the classes, and hence the contract.
                    </para>
                </blockquote>
        		The alternative of contract-last development is <emphasis>contract-first development</emphasis>.
        		Using this approach, the service and data contract are leading. Spring-WS focusses on contract-first Web
        		service development, because is considered to be a best practice. After all, the actual XML that is sent
        		across the wire is more important than the Java code that is used to implement it.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
