<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"> 
<chapter id="what-is-spring-ws">
    <title>What is Spring Web Services?</title>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>
            Spring Web Services (Spring-WS) is a product of the Spring community focused on creating document-driven 
            Web services.
            Spring Web Services aims to facilitate contract-first SOAP service development, allowing for the creation of
            flexible web services using one of the many ways to manipulate XML payloads.
            The product is based on Spring itself, which means you can use the Spring concepts such as dependency 
            injection as an integral part of your Web service.
        </para>
        <para>
            People use Spring-WS for many reasons, but most are drawn to it after finding alternative SOAP stacks 
            lacking when it comes to following Web service best practices.
            Spring-WS makes the best practice an easy practice. This includes practices such as the WS-I basic profile,
            Contract-First development, and having a loose coupling between contract and implementation.
            The other key features of Spring Web services are:
        </para>
        <formalpara>
            <title>Powerful mappings</title>
            <para>
                You can distribute incoming XML request to any object, depending on message payload, SOAP Action header, 
                or an XPath expression.
            </para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
            <title>XML API support</title>
            <para>
                Incoming XML messages can be handled in standard JAXP APIs such as DOM, SAX, and StAX, but also JDOM, 
                dom4j, XOM, or even marshalling technologies.
            </para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
            <title>Flexible XML Marshalling</title>
            <para>
                The Object/XML Mapping module in the Spring Web Services distribution supports JAXB 1 and 2, Castor, 
                XMLBeans, JiBX, and XStream. And because it is a separate module, you can use it in non-Web services code 
                as well.
            </para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
            <title>Reuses your Spring expertise</title>
            <para>
                Spring-WS uses Spring application contexts for all configuration, which should  help Spring developers 
                get up-to-speed nice and quickly. Also, the architecture of Spring-WS resembles that of Spring-MVC.
            </para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
            <title>Supports WS-Security</title>
            <para>
                WS-Security allows you to sign SOAP messages, encrypt and decrypt them, or authenticate against them.
            </para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
            <title>Integrates with Acegi Security</title>
            <para>
                The WS-Security implementation of Spring Web Services provides integration with 
                <ulink url="http://acegisecurity.org">Acegi Security</ulink>. This means you can use your existing Acegi 
                configuration for your SOAP service as well.
            </para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
            <title>Built by Maven</title>
            <para>
                This assists you in effectively reusing the Spring Web Services artifacts in your own Maven-based projects.
            </para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
            <title>Apache license</title>
            <para>
                You can confidently use Spring-WS in your project.
            </para>
        </formalpara>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Runtime environment</title>
        <para>
            Spring Web Services runs within a standard Java 1.3 Runtime Environment. It also supports Java 5.0, 
            although the Java types which are specific to this release are packaged in a separate modules with the 
            suffix "tiger" in their JAR filename.
            Spring-WS consists of a number of modules, which are described in the remainder of this section.
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
            <para>
                The XML module (<filename>spring-xml.jar</filename>) contains various XML support classes for Spring Web 
                Services. This module is mainly targeted at the Spring-WS framework itself, and not a Web service 
                developers.
            </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The Core package (<filename>spring-ws-core.jar</filename> and <filename>spring-ws-core-tiger.jar</filename>)
                     is the central part of the Web services 
                    functionality. It provides the central <link linkend="web-service-messages">
                    <classname>WebServiceMessage</classname></link> and <link linkend="soap-message">
                    <classname>SoapMessage</classname></link> interfaces, the <link linkend="server">server-side</link> 
                    framework, with powerful message dispatching, and the various support classes for implementing Web service
                    endpoints; and the <link linkend="client">client-side</link> <classname>WebServiceTemplate</classname>.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The <link linkend="security">Security</link> package (<filename>spring-ws-security.jar</filename>)
                    provides a WS-Security implementation that integrates
                    with the core Web service package. It allows you to add principal tokens, sign, and decrypt and encrypt SOAP
                    messages. Addtionally, it allows you to leverage your existing Acegi security implementation for
                    authentication and authorization.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The <link linkend="oxm">OXM</link> package (<filename>spring-oxm.jar</filename> and 
                    <filename>spring-oxm-tiger.jar</filename>) provides integration for popular XML marshalling APIs, including
                    JAXB 1 and 2. Using the OXM package means that you benefit from a unified exception hierarchy, and can wire
                    up your favorite XML marshalling technology easily.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
            The following figure illustrates the modules, and the dependencies between them. Arrows indicate 
            dependencies, i.e. Spring-WS Core depends on Spring-XML and Spring-OXM.
            <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject role="fo">
                        <imagedata fileref="src/docbkx/resources/images/spring-deps.png"
                                   format="PNG" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <imageobject role="html">
                        <imagedata fileref="images/spring-deps.png"
                                   format="PNG" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>
                            Dependencies between Spring-WS modules
                        </para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
